I'm Uma Mukara.
I lead the product as head of
resilience testing at Harness.
I've also had a few more
stints to my career.
I created two open source projects
that are at the CNCF incubation level
for the last seven, eight years.
Open EBS, Litmus Chaos are the
two projects that I created.
Also built three different companies.
Now I'm leading resilience
testing innovations and
product building at Harness.
What I want to take you
through today is really, okay.
The SRE persona especially that they
get a little bit of a different view
depending on where they worked, right?
Reliability versus resilience
is the key difference.
Most of them think it's all same, right?
But there is a key difference between
re- resilience and reliability.
I really wanted to talk in three
parts today for SREs primarily, right?
Understanding reliability
versus resilience.
Second one is why SREs need to
care about chaos engineering.
How many of chaos engineering?
The reason why I came into the
industry is to help practice
chaos engineering by SREs, right?
Everybody understands why chaos
engineering, but they don't
practice because they're not
allowed to practice, right?
And that's where you need to understand
reliability versus resilience.
I want you to walk away
with that thought process.
And then good news is that with this
new AI, most of the work that , you
had to do to convince your bosses
that, yeah, we had to do chaos
engineering will be done by AI.
So you can actually walk
with the report, right?
I would that's the third part that I want
to cover, that what can you do with AI
to go and convince that you can, you need
to increase the resilience following it.
So what is resilience?
Before I get to that, what is resilience?
These are some of the well-known
incidents that have happened
on the providers, right?
Incident you are, as a SRS, you are
trying to recover from the incidents that
your product is going through, right?
Your service is going through.
But there are also incidents that will
happen because of somebody else, right?
AWS goes down.
You will start seeing incidents.
There is an incident at AWS, but then
you will also have incidents because
your system started malfunctioning
because your provider is not good, right?
So that is the, so you are losing
reliability because your product
is not serving the customers.
Similarly that entire reliability
issue has come because somebody
else malfunctioned, right?
AWS, CrowdStrike incident, like
GitHub is not working, right?
So it can be anything, right?
So that's why you need to be resilient.
Even though your external
providers are not functioning
properly, they had incident.
So what?
You need to be resilient so that
you don't get into incidents, right?
So as SREs, we think that I need
to put all the scripts, everything,
like she had a great talk about
how they manage incidents.
All those are great, right?
How do you fix problems?
That's definitely one of the
key functions of SREs, right?
How do you go and operate your systems
optimally, make them available as long
as possible so that your uptime and your
SLOs to your customers are met, right?
So at the same time, resilience
is very important, right?
When something goes wrong in your
systems, or when your service providers,
even though they gave nine, triple
nines, four nines, finance has the
reliability, your providers, right?
There is still not 100%.
At some point of time,
they're going to go down.
And at that time, will you also go down?
If you go down, then, you cannot
give same reliability as them, right?
So you need to be more resilient, right?
So resilient is about when
somebody tries to push you.
At some point of time,
you'll fall down, right?
If the entire drone strike happens, like
what it did in AWS data centers in Dubai,
things are going to go down, right?
So how fast you can come back, right?
So you need to declare DR, it
goes to somewhere else, right?
And then is it like one
hour, two hours, five hours?
Audio clusters will never come back.
Clusters, AWS will give you the
other cluster somewhere else.
But with your application come
back, your data may not come back.
So that's really the
resilience about, right?
And SRs need to care about that also.
Almost all the time,
everything works fine.
Right?
99.99 reliability means that you have
seven hours of downtime in a year.
Okay.
Those seven hours can be
caused by many issues, right?
It could be issues in your product like
what the prior speaker talked about.
They had an issue in
their own platform, right?
So they solved it brilliantly.
That may not be all the case, right?
So okay, she recovered
everything, fixed everything.
Can she change that now, seven
hours of downtime expectation
in the year to four hours?
No.
Because wherever they're
hosted, AWS, that can go down.
So eventually, something will go down.
That's what we learned in the
prior s - session as well.
So how to make yourself resilient.
That's the answer.
That's what resilience is about, right?
So reliability is a lo - a-
about being available.
Resilience is about can
you come back faster?
I, I can bend.
I'm still functioning.
That is still good, right?
Latency is 10 milliseconds
to 20 milliseconds.
It's still good.
But you need to see whether
when 20 millisecond latency
will actually stop some of your
services from functioning, right?
So that's about testing the
resilience of the system.
So resilience and reliability
are two different goals.
Reliability often both
are driven by SREs, right?
You cannot say that I don't
care about resilience.
You'll still get fired.
If you say that I don't care about
reliability, you'll get fired.
But re- reliability is
definitely is taught more.
Google SRE book talks about reliability.
There is like a small
chapter somewhere there.
You need to do chaos engineering also.
That's resilience, right?
So resilience is as important as
reliability because at some point of time,
if you really want to get promotions,
you should focus on re- resilience.
So I used to joke to my SREs, right?
If you want to keep your
job, focus on reliability.
If you want to get yourself
promoted, focus on resilience.
Because when something goes wrong,
if you're still resilient, and if
your competitor goes down, you'll get
promoted because you did everything
that is needed to stay up even
though some problems happened, right?
So you not only stop this from
getting bad repetition with our large
number of customers, you're also
making sure that you are creating a
differentiation about our reliability
compared to competitors, right?
So it's really about
controlling the blast radius.
When something goes wrong, only this
region is affected or every, all
other regions are affected, right?
And how can you come back from
something, that has already bad happened?
Do I have the right run books?
Are my Saudis trained well enough?
Do I understand the
complexity of my system?
All this are learned when you put the
focus on resilience of the system.
So yeah, resilience is important
because the system will always work.
At some point it doesn't, right?
The seven hours of downtime expectations
of every large system, right?
So you need to focus on resilience, right?
So that's where chaos
engineering comes up, right?
So you need to put some faults into
your system because faults will
happen onto your system and then test
if you are resilient or not, right?
And a lot of people think chaos
engineering is breaking things on purpose.
That is a very common.
Chaos engineering is throw some
spanner into the wheel and go away.
Okay, that is like you're
destroying the systems, right?
Chaos engineering is really about
understanding the resilience and getting
some data about resilience, right?
A lot of weaknesses may
be hidden in your systems.
Just knowing what your
weaknesses are will be enough to
increase your rel- reliability.
Let's say that, you have a big
bug in your system database.
If it wa - it's, let's say, active, right?
A particular scenario of a database
going down, you have application bug,
and it takes a lot of time to resolve.
It's known.
Just knowing that itself, right?
You can go prepared better
on how to recover, right?
Or reducing the damage.
Let's say that you don't
need to do anything.
You have very important customer
who are paying millions of dollars
for you, most important customer.
You can just call the CIO of that person
or when you meet, "Hey, we have an issue.
I know we have SLA. But if unfortunately
this happens, we do have an, a problem
and we'll have to also downtime."
Just tell that.
That itself will save you
from losing that customer.
"Oh, thank you for being open
to your, give me an action plan.
You'll give.
It might take one year
to solve that problem.
But if you don't know that weakness,
then it's a big problem, right?
The years of relationship that you build
with your customer can be gone just
in one second if you are on a bad day.
Okay?
So chaos engineering is about
finding weaknesses, right?
Knowing the risks of your system.
And once you know the system, it's easy.
SREs can find the weaknesses and
tell the development team, "Guys,
you need to fix it." Or the QA teams
can find the weaknesses and tell the
SRA teams, "Guys, we have issues.
So save yourself from
the embarrassment, right?
You need to go and do better run books
or go and, put some communication plan
to your customers appropriately, right?
And let's talk about it in the next
quarterly planning, so on and so forth.
And if the same incident
happens again and again, right?
So look, you need to keep doing
this again and again, not in
production, but in QA, right?
So let's go do some chaos tests
properly so that we can test our
runbooks properly in the lower systems.
That's chaos engineering.
The cost of not doing chaos
engineering, we need to find
some myth busters here, right?
Everybody thinks that we are 99% nine.
We talked about it.
Just being four nines, four nines
doesn't mean that, everything is fine.
Things can go bad.
And, whatever, all the good thing
that you built around this four nines
can be gone in just two hours, right?
So chaos engineering can stop
you from getting there, right?
And we are, we're testing staging.
We don't need to do it in production.
Things could be a lot different.
So game days are important, right?
So you need to test here and
there, at least with the low
intensity in production also.
Break things in production
and see how it goes, right?
So Canadian deployments
can help there as well.
And the biggest myth is thinking
that our, we have a fantastic team.
Yeah, we have fantastic team.
The, your SREs are thinking
that my guys are good.
My QA team is thinking
that my SREs are good.
But they don't communicate.
I just introduced a fantastic
feature, me as an architect developer.
And my PMs are told me that
this is going to bring us a lot
more revenue, so introduce it.
And I didn't communicate that to
SREs and an incident happened.
And they don't know how to record it back.
So the complexities of the systems,
they keep changing all the time, right?
Or another example is SREs have upgraded
their infrastructure to put more
redundancy or better configuration,
better cache systems whatever.
And they forgot to tell the architects,
enterprise architects on the other side,
and they know that there is an issue.
The system is not designed
for such a improvement, right?
So they don't communicate.
And again, it's a problem.
Chaos engineering actually helps
putting tabs on the reality check.
Okay, you are people do not know that a
new dependence is introduced or they don't
know how to recover from such a system.
Let me get some water, please.
Oops, sorry.
So chaos engineering or a chaos
experiment is about introducing
certain expected failure parts.
Those are the pink boxes, right?
And the green boxes are checking if
your system is still okay or not, right?
The chaos faults also can
be very tricky, right?
Everybody tests that, if I pull up
network plug, things will continue
to work because there is a renincy.
But when you pull a plug, there's
more load on the other network switch.
Or load balancing schemes change.
More applications behave
slightly differently.
They are still working.
At exact same time, some
other thing happens, right?
So under that behavior, introducing
a new fault, a memory leak might
happen when the memory leak happens.
And at the same time, if the
network provider also goes slow,
then big incident can happen.
So it's really about taking an incident
and then exactly trying to recreate
that incident through multiple fault
injections in certain sequence, right?
And when that sequence happen,
let's go and find weaknesses, right?
Those are the green boxes.
You need to see that my logins
are working fine or even the
latencies could have been increased.
Error rates on my APM systems
are increasing a little bit.
Still functioning, but error
rate should not have increased.
That's a weakness, right?
So the idea of chaos experiment is
to really find weaknesses, right?
Not really find very
big bugs, but weakness.
I'm under the weather.
I have a weakness today, right?
I cannot run, but I'm still functional.
But you should be resilient
to those weaknesses, right?
So that's the whole idea of building very
strong resilience systems by SREs, right?
Now that requests chaos engineering.
We all understood that, right?
So the SRS role is really
defining those green boxes, right?
Not everybody knows what
those green boxes are.
Let me give you an example, right?
I'm an architect.
I build a good design and give
it to my implementation team.
It's all working well, right?
And somebody tests it, puts
it in the production, right?
In production that they're, the
systems are like very large,
too many interdependencies,
so on and so forth, right?
Only an observability expert
will know what all to look for.
You go to your NOC, old NOCs, so
on and so forth, or your Dynatist
Datadog, multiple dashboards.
You are observing everything.
And tho - that, those parameters are not
given back to the engineering, right?
So you have to provide that knowledge
back to the engineering teams so
that whenever the test, a test is
in pre-production, they actually
go and check these SLIs, right?
Service level indicators are
the key aspect of building a
good chaos experiment, right?
And identify the blast radius.
There is a second
important thing for a SRE.
You should know if this one goes
down, it affects only a certain area
or the entire system is down, right?
Then you can actually change
your runbooks in a better way.
And then you should force your
teams to run chaos engineering
in in staging, right?
At least to some extent, right?
I know permissions won't
be given in production.
That's why you had to go and force,
okay, at least run in testing and see
this observability metrics, right?
So that's one of the rules, right?
And then try to push them
towards resilience gates, right?
So this is a culture thing.
How many of your deployment pipelines
have the knowledge of resilience testing?
Everybody has, okay, code
coverage, test coverage, right?
Any regressions?
If new regressions don't deploy and
you go to SRs and take some exception.
I know there is small regression,
but our customer needs it.
Let's push it, right?
This is a very common
practice in the industry.
Are we doing the same thing
for resilience, right?
How resilient is this new release
compared to the old release, right?
So try to push your management
to think of overall reliability
in the lens of resilience, right?
Of course, they push a product
in new release, but, we are SREs.
We are the ones who will be affected.
So we should go back and tell, yeah, they
give me permissions to test in production.
No?
At least put some resilience get slower.
If they put no also, that means
they don't care about resilience.
Then you escalate, right?
So then they should do resilience.
There's some techniques that will help
them start initiating at least some
chaos experimentation in staging, right?
So at the same time, after they deploy,
you should still run some game days,
do some as minimum as possible to start
with some chaos testing in production.
That'll really help.
And it takes time, right?
Somewhere somebody has to
start doing chaos testing.
Introduce some programs, right?
We are doing first game
day for our organization.
That means, we have started the idea of
building better resilience systems, right?
So from there, all the way till going
to predictive level where I know if
a particular resilience issue happens
a fault happens, this is going to go
and a particular system gets affected.
So let me go auto run my
chaos experiments, right?
So that is fully autonomous.
Nobody in the world does that.
Not even electrics, right?
But we need to get to at
least level three, right?
Most of the organizations four
years ago were at level one, right?
But I see that industries move
from level one to level two now.
Most of the organizations have an
idea of chaos engineering, right?
But it's good to be at a good
integrated level where basic
systems are aware of chaos testing.
And the most critical services
are going through chaos
testing in lower environments.
And minimum game days
are being run, right?
Just DR testing is
complaints mandated, right?
At least few game days are
happening in, in a year.
So that's where you need to push, right?
That's the idea that you
have to have as an SRE.
Now, going back to the third
part that I talked about.
Traditional approach is what
we have talked about, right?
AI can actually help, right?
How powerful this new
LLMs have happened, right?
So six months ago, I was not sure, but
now I'm very convinced that they can do
almost everything that you want, right?
To provide it the private
data that you are giving.
You feed the private data,
your local system data to AI.
It gives you some knowledge
that you cannot think of, right?
So risk discoveries can happen
even without running chaos testing.
Chaos experiments, AIs can
actually go and, yeah, I looked
at your configurations, logs,
and here are probably the
resilience risks that you have.
So that is a starting point for you to
go and say that, "I looked at my system."
As an SRE, you can go and tell, "Hey,
give me your, here is my deployment
data. I just deployed. You can even go
to your observability system and get
all the deployment data and feed that
to your MCP, one of through MCP, you get
that data and then feed it to your cloud
or any other LLM, and then say that,
give me the resilience risk report."
You can take that report and then go
into your management and say that,
look, the risks have increased from
last two releases to this release.
LLM is telling that, right?
You don't need to worry about
what those risks are, but at
least the risks are increasing.
Somebody's telling.
So take a look at it.
Implement some parts of chaos
engineering so on and so forth.
So that's the idea that
you can take and go.
All right?
So passive risk detection is
going to be the future, right?
For example, we as the primary product
vendor, we offer features like just
by looking at your Argo CD data or any
other harness CD data, we can tell that
you actually have the following risks.
And these are the type of incidents
that you might get, right?
And here are the chaos experimentations
that you may need to do.
Do you want me to do?
Okay, I'll create
everything automatically.
It's all prompt-based, right?
So this is where you're going.
So take a look at this
passive risk detection.
Active risk detection is what I talked
about earlier, where you have to run
chaos experience to find the risk, right?
You can even do the same detection
passively without running just by feeding
your deployment data, incident data
service data to your AI through MCP.
So a lot of things can be AI generated.
So doing chaos experimentation could
be 10 times easier now than earlier.
Getting permissions also is easier
because we go and give the report.
Look, you are going to have a lot of risk.
And it's on your head then.
I'm telling you, right?
So now do you want me to start
something in chaos or not?
No.
Okay.
You go to his boss and get him
fired and get another one, right?
So it's easy for you to influence
that there are real risks because
AI can give you the data, right?
The resilience first future
is how it's going to look.
Earlier reactive failures, most of
the chaos engineering happens because
a lot of incident happened, right?
A new SVP came and said yeah, I know.
I'm introducing chaos engineering."
And then last five years, we have seen
shift left chaos engineering put all
the chaos tests into pipelines, right?
A lot of knowledge has
been paused in that.
But next five years, you would
say autonomous resilience, right?
AI will go predict the risk,
create the chaos experiments.
All you need to do is
don't stop it, right?
And be careful.
Just guide the right data right level
of chaos testing that you need to do.
So we are walking, as an
industry, we are walking towards
autonomous resilience, right?
So those are the points that I wanted
to give you, the idea of resilience,
importance of resilience, your
role as an SRE in doing resilience,
where the industry's going, right?
You can read more on it
either on harness, right?
So I lead the product
for resilience testing.
Chaos is my core, but we also club load
testing and DR testing because we want
to look at the failures that systems
can undergo as a holistic thing, right?
Everything is doing good, but with
load, things can fail again, right?
And if worst case scenarios,
are you recovering faster in
disaster recovery mode, right?
So on and so on.
That's what harness resilience
testing is about, right?
Thank you.